A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of James A. Gardner FA629
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of James A. Gardner
1971-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Gardner, James A., 1943-
Ford Foundation
FA629
0.76 Cubic Feet
The Latin America and Caribbean Papers of James A. Gardner document his activities and those of the International Division primarily for the period Gardner served as the Program Officer/Coordinator for the Caribbean from 1974 to 1977. They were transferred to the Foundation's Archives in July 1982. These papers consist of correspondence, and reports which were retained in the office of James Gardner when he served in New York as the Program Officer/ Coordinator for the Caribbean.
Biographical / Historical
James A. Gardner, Ford Foundation Representative for the Latin America and Caribbean office of the International Division, was a member of the Foundation staff from 1969 until 1981. During this period, he held the following positions:
- February 1977, Representative, LAC, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, ID
- September 1974, Program Officer, LAC, Coordinator for the Caribbean, New York, ID
- September 1973, Program Officer, LAC, on one year study leave at the Harvard Law School, ID
- February 1972, Program Officer and Assistant to Head, LAC, ID
- August 1971, Assistant Program Officer and Assistant to Head, LAC, ID
- July 1969, Assistant to the Representative, LAC, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, ID
James Gardner was born July 22, 1943. He received his B.A. degree in 1965 from Harvard University. In 1968, he earned the J.D. degree from the Yale Law School.
Prior to Gardner's career with the Ford Foundation, he held the following positions:
- 1966 - 1968 Resident Counselor and Advisor, Yale University
- 1968 - 1969 Assistant Director of Admissions and Tutor in Social Sciences and Law, Harvard University
After his departure from the Ford Foundation, Mr. Gardner accepted the position of President of Lewis and Clark College of Portland, Oregon.
Scope and Contents
The two boxes of correspondence and reports which constitute the LAC Papers of James A. Gardner, document his activities and a number of those of the International Division for the years 1971 to 1977.
The papers contain material on the subject of human rights, including the Foundation's policy statement regarding biomedical research and the use of human beings as subjects.
The files discuss the subject of law and its social obligations. In particular, they illuminate such topics as law and development, social change, and how it relates to the development of human talent; the future of public interest law; and Gardner's work, "The Legal Profession and the Third World," which deals with American assistance to legal education in Latin America in the 1960's.
The papers also contain related correspondence between LAC staff members and individuals who applied for the FY76 Foundation sponsored Caribbean Fellowship Fund, but whose applications were incomplete.
The Correspondence Files document the day-to-day program activity of Gardner during his New York based tenure as the Program Officer/Coordinator for the Caribbean.
Arrangement
The Latin America and Caribbean Papers of James A. Gardner, are divided into two series:
I. Subject Files
II. Correspondence Files
Arrangement within the series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by Gardner's office.
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports and publications have been pulled and accessioned into the FF Archives. A cross-reference sheet located within the folders denotes accessioned reports. A list of titles removed from the papers is appended to this register. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been removed.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Subject Files, 1971-1976; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Subject Files (1971-1976), are the most substantive. They contain material on the following: human rights; law and development; law and social sciences; law and social change; public interest law; and FY76 Caribbean fellowship fund (incomplete) application requests. The material consists of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports.
  Arrangement
  The files are arranged in reverse calendar order. Within each folder, the files are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Human Rights, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1-20)
  - Law and Development, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 21-35)
  - Law and Social Sciences, 1972-1973, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 36-39)
  - Law and Social Change, 1976 October (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Public Interest Law, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 41-43)
  - FY76 Caribbean fellowship fund (incomplete) application requests, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
- Correspondence Files, 1974-1976; II
  Series II, Correspondence Files (1974-1976), document the office activities of Gardner during his tenure as the Program Officer/Coordinator for the Caribbean. Recipients of his outgoing correspondence and interoffice memoranda include FF colleagues, grantee and membership organizations, and individuals and organizations seeking grants.
  - 1976 (Box 2, Folder 46-55)
  - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 56-67)
  - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 68-79)